Register of the John G. Wright Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
John G. Wright papers
1933-1977
92033
Hoover Institution Archives
9 manuscript boxes (3.6 linear feet)
Speeches and writings, correspondence, resolutions, theses, and notes, relating to Marxian theory, the translation of works of Leon Trotsky, Trotskyist activities in the United States and abroad, and analysis of the post-World War II Chinese and Eastern European states.
Wright, John G., 1902-1956.
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1992.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1902 Born as Joseph Vanzler in Samarkand, Uzbekistan, in the Russian Empire
circa 1914 Emigrated to the United States
circa 1920 Graduated from Harvard University. Became a professional chemist
1933 Joined the Communist League of America (subsequently Socialist Workers Party)
1933-1940 Literary collaborator and translator of Leon Trotsky
1939-1956 Member, National Committee, Socialist Workers Party
1956 Died in New York City
Scope and Content Note
John G. Wright (the political and pen name of Joseph Vanzler) was a leader of the Socialist Workers Party of the United States from the 1930s to the 1950s. Wright was heavily involved with theoretical, journalistic and publishing-house work of the party. A polyglot, he translated texts from various languages into English for publication. His collaborative work with Leon Trotsky was of particular significance. Wright translated many of Trotsky's writings into English for the first time. During Trotsky's period of residence in Mexico at the end of his life (1937-1940), Wright, in New York City, corresponded with him regularly and, having access to major American academic libraries, provided him with Russian-language research materials to support his writing projects, especially his biography of Joseph Stalin. The papers thus shed light on Trotsky's literary activities and on the publishing history of Stalin. Post-World War II materials in the collection also document debates within the Trotskyist movement on analysis of the Chinese and Eastern European states, and the internal struggle within the Socialist Workers Party involving the faction led by Bert Cochran and George Clarke.
The John G. Wright Papers were formerly housed at the Library of Social History in New York City. The Hoover Institution Archives acquired them in 1992.
Fourth International.; Socialist Workers Party.; Trotsky, Leon, 1879-1940.; China.; Communism--United States.; Communism.; Europe, Eastern.; United States--Politics and government.
- Biographical File, 1956-1977
  Scope and Contents note
  Obituaries, tributes, lists, and material for projected memorial volume.
  - Obituaries and memorial tributes, 1956 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    Includes tributes by James P. Cannon, George Novack and Morris Stein.
  - Lists of papers and books, 1933-1997, undated (Box-folder 1: 2)
    Includes list of selected Socialist Workers Party records.
  - Projected Pathfinder Press memorial volume, 1977 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    Draft table of contents, draft introductory matter, and working materials.
- Correspondence File, 1934-1956
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Includes some letters by third parties. Editorial correspondence of Bert Cochran from 1945 to 1947 is interfiled with that of Wright. Wright and Cochran shared editorial duties on The Fourth International during this period.
  - General, 1943-1955 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Baghavan, R.S. (Ceylon), 1948-1954 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Bartell, Mike, 1945-1947 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Birchman, Robert L., 1945 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Braden, Mark, 1945 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Breitman, George, 1943-1955 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Canfield, Cass (Harper and Brothers; re Leon Trotsky manuscripts), 1937 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Cannon, James P., 1944-1954 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Carlson, Grace, 1943-1947 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Chester, Bob, 1945-1955 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Clarke, George, 1945 (Box-folder 1: 14)
    Includes 1953 memorandum about Clarke.
  - Cochran, Bert, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 1: 15)
    Includes 1953 resolutions of Cochran-Clarke faction.
  - Copeland, Vince, 1944-1946 (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Cornell, Charles, 1946 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Creel, Warren, 1944-1947 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - Curtiss, Charles, 1945-1948 (Box-folder 1: 19)
    Includes 1939 note from Lillian Curtiss in Coyoacán.
  - Davenport, William, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 1: 20)
  - Dobbs, Farrell, 1945-1953 (Box-folder 1: 21)
  - Dollinger, Sol (United Auto Workers), 1945 (Box-folder 1: 22)
    Includes press releases and letters of protest re beating of Dollinger.
  - Dowson, Ross (Canada), 1946 (Box-folder 1: 23)
  - Dunayevskaya, Raya, 1937-1948 (Box-folder 1: 24)
    Includes letters from Coyoacán.
  - Dunne, Vincent Raymond, 1945 (Box-folder 1: 25)
  - Forkosch, Morris D. (re Trotsky heirs), 1941 (Box-folder 1: 26)
  - Frank, Pierre (France), 1945 (Box-folder 1: 27)
  - Frankel, Jan (Coyoacán), 1937 (Box-folder 1: 28)
  - Geldman, Max, 1945-1952 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Geller, Jules, 1944-1951 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Glass, Frank, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Goldman, Albert (re Trotsky manuscripts), 1941-1945 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Gordon, Eloise, 1944-1947 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Gordon, Sam, 1945-1948 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Hansen, Reba, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Haston, Jock (Great Britain), 1946 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Healy, Gerry (Great Britain), 1952-1953 (Folder 2: 9)
  - Karsner, Rose, 1951 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Keemer, Edgar, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Kitt, Bill, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Konikow, Antoinette (mother-in-law of Wright), 1934-1946 (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Kovalesky, Theodore, 1943-1947 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - Lee, Grace, 1947 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - Leinwand, Rose (sister of Wright), 1943-1945 (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - Liberty (re Trotsky manuscripts), 1938 (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - Malamuth, Charles (re Trotsky manuscripts), 1938-1940 (Box-folder 2: 18)
  - Mandel, Ernest (Belgium), 1945-1953 (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - Marcy, Sam, 1956 (Box-folder 2: 20)
  - Mei, Lei Dar (re China), 1955 (Box-folder 2: 21)
  - Moreno, Nahuel (Argentina), 1955 (Box-folder 2: 22)
  - Morrow, Felix, 1943 (Box-folder 2: 23)
  - Murphy, Patrick, 1944 (Box-folder 2: 24)
  - New International (re Trotsky manuscripts), 1939 (Box-folder 2: 25)
  - Novack, George, 1945-1952 (Box-folder 2: 26)
  - O'Brien, Vaughan T. (Coyoacán), 1938-1939 (Box-folder 2: 27)
  - Olshausen, George G., 1947-1948 (Box-folder 2: 28)
  - O'Rourke, Walter (Coyoacán), 1940 (Box-folder 2: 29)
  - Pablo, Michel (France), 1948 (Box-folder 2: 30)
  - Roberts, Dan, 1944 (Box-folder 2: 31)
  - Rubinstein, Moisei (Mexico), 1936 (Box-folder 2: 32)
  - Saettone, Ruben (re Argentina), 1945 (Box-folder 2: 33)
  - Selander, Ted, 1945-1947 (Box-folder 2: 34)
  - Sinclair, Louis (Great Britain), 1948 (Box-folder 2: 35)
  - Stein, Morris and Sylvia, 1943-1948 (Box-folder 2: 36)
  - Swabeck, Arne, 1942-1955 (Box-folder 2: 37)
  - Torchia, Rose, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 2: 38)
  - Trainor, Larry and Augusta, 1944-1947 (Box-folder 2: 39)
  - Trotskaia, Nataliia Sedova, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 40)
  - Trotsky, Leon, 1937-1940 (Box-folder 2: 41)
  - Van Heijenoort, Jean, 1937-1946 (Box-folder 2: 42)
  - Vanzler, Edith (first wife of Wright), 1945 (Box-folder 2: 43)
  - Vanzler, Tyl (son of Wright), 1945-1953 (Box-folder 2: 44)
  - Walker, Charles R. (re Trotsky manuscripts), 1937 (Box-folder 2: 45)
  - Weber, Sara (Coyoacán), 1937-1938 (Box-folder 2: 46)
  - Weiss, Murry, 1942-1951 (Box-folder 2: 47)
  - Weiss, Myra Tanner, 1944 (Box-folder 2: 48)
  - Wild, Mr. (Great Britain; re Trotsky manuscripts), 1937 (Box-folder 2: 49)
  - Wolfe, Bernard (Coyoacán), 1937 (Box-folder 2: 50)
  - Wolfe, Bertram D., 1941 (Box-folder 2: 51)
- Speeches and Writings, 1933-1956
  Arranged chronologically.
  - "American Perspectives,", circa 1933 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - "A Few Facts" [re France], 1934 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - "Proposed Theses on the Role and Nature of the Revolutionary Party,", 1934 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Untitled speech re Paterson, New Jersey, textile strike, 1934 (Box-folder 3: 4)
    Notes and working materials.
  - "The Bolshevik-Leninists in the SFIO" and La Vérité, 1935 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Untitled debate with Sidney Hook re Marxism, circa 1935 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Letter to the editor, New International, re Sidney Hook, 1935 March 25 (Box-folder 3: 7)
    Typescript and cover letter.
  - "The Fate of a Marxist Classic," The Accumulation of Capital, 1935 July 8 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - "Perspectives of the American Revolution,", 1936 (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - Untitled speech re Moscow Trials, 1937 March (Box-folder 3: 10)
    Notes and drafts.
  - "Roosevelt Beats the War Drums," speech, 1937 November 12 (Box-folder 3: 11)
    Announcement, notes, drafts and working materials.
  - The Truth about Kronstadt, 1938 (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - Untitled speech re GPU murders and kidnappings, 1938 (Box-folder 3: 13)
    Notes, drafts and working materials.
  - "The Ideological Captives of the Bourgeoisie,", 1939 July 15 (Box-folder 3: 14)
  - "Shachtman and the Slippery Ice of Russian History," speech, 1939-1940 (Box-folder 3: 15)
  - Outline History of Russian Bolshevism, 1940
    - Book One (Box-folder 3: 16)
    - Book Two (Box-folder 3: 17-18)
    - Notes and drafts (Box-folder 3: 19)
    - Edited typescript, 1977 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Untitled speech re splits in Bolshevik history, 1940 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Untitled speech re situation in Soviet Union, 1940 December 26 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - "What Are Russia's Chances?" [re German invasion], 1941 June (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Untitled speech re party organization, Socialist Workers Party convention, 1942 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Untitled speech, anniversary of founding of Second International, 1942 May 1 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Untitled speech, anniversary of death of Leon Trotsky, 1942 August (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Exchange of notes with other Socialist Workers Party leaders re revolutionary defeatism, 1942-1944 (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Untitled speech, anniversary of death of V. I. Lenin, 1943 January (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Untitled speech, Socialist Workers Party National Committee plenum, 1943 October 31 - November 1 (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - "How Long Before the Revolution?", 1944 (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - Untitled speech re Germany, 1944 (Box-folder 4: 12)
  - Untitled speech, anniversary of Russian Revolution, 1944 November (Box-folder 4: 13)
  - "The British Labor Victory: Its Meaning for the American Workers," national lecture tour, 1945 September - November (Box-folder 4: 14)
  - "Stalin," speech re publication of Leon Trotsky's, 1946 (Box-folder 4: 15)
  - "Theses on the American Revolution,", 1946 (Box-folder 4: 16)
  - Untitled writing re Soviet Union, 1947 (Box-folder 4: 17)
  - Untitled speech re war and depression, 1947 (Box-folder 4: 18)
  - "The Twin Evils: War and Depression," May Day speech, 1947 May 3 (Box-folder 4: 19)
  - Untitled remarks, educational meeting re British Labour Party, 1947 September 18 (Box-folder 4: 20)
  - Untitled writing re Yugoslavia, 1948 (Box-folder 4: 21)
  - "The Soviet Union Today," speech, 1949 (Box-folder 4: 22)
  - Untitled speech re devaluation, 1949 October 6 (Box-folder 4: 23)
  - Untitled speech, anniversary of Russian Revolution, 1949 November (Box-folder 4: 24)
  - Untitled speech re Yugoslavia, Socialist Workers Party convention, 1950 (Box-folder 4: 25)
  - Untitled speech re Eastern Europe, Socialist Workers Party National Committee plenum, 1950 February (Box-folder 4: 26)
  - Review of Benjamin I. Schwartz, "Chinese Communism and the Rise of Mao,", circa 1951 (Box-folder 4: 27)
  - Untitled remarks, unidentified meeting, 1951 January (Box-folder 4: 28)
  - "The Colonial Revolution: Greatest Event of Our Time," speech, 1951 November 30 (Box-folder 4: 29)
  - Foreword and notes to Leon Trotsky, "The First Five Years of the Communist International," Volume II, 1953 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Untitled speech in opposition to Cochran-Clarke faction, 1953 (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - "Stalin and Stalinism," speech, 1953 April 17 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - "Cochranite Level of Discussion: Mechanical Thinking Plus Sophistry Plus Slander," speech, 1953 May 3 (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - Untitled remarks re Cochran-Clarke faction, Socialist Workers Party National Committee plenum, 1953 May 28 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - "Djilas Case,", 1954 (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - Untitled May Day speech, 1954 May 1 (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - Untitled writing re Hu Feng purge in China, 1955 (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - "Preliminary Notes on Automation,", 1955 January 3 (Box-folder 5: 9)
  - Untitled resolution on colonialism, 1955 June 29 (Box-folder 5: 10)
  - "The Soviet Union Today," draft resolution, 1955 August 12 (Box-folder 5: 11)
  - "Draft Amendment on the Third Chinese Revolution" [with Farrell Dobbs and Morris Stein], 1955 September 13 (Box-folder 5: 12)
  - Untitled writing re 20th Congress of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union, 1956 (Box-folder 5: 13)
  - "ABC of Marxism," International Workers School lecture series, (repeated for many years), undated
    - General (Box-folder 5: 14)
    - Dialectics (Box-folder 5: 15)
    - Historical materialism (Box-folder 6: 1)
    - Marxian economics (Box-folder 6: 2)
  - "Bolshevik Traditions (Intra-Party Conduct),", undated (Box-folder 6: 3)
  - "The Collapse of the Second International,", undated (Box-folder 6: 4)
  - "Documents for the History of the Comintern,", undated (Box-folder 6: 5)
  - "Kamo: The Story of a Worker-Bolshevik,", undated (Box-folder 6: 6)
  - "Marxism and the Law,", undated (Box-folder 6: 7)
  - "Marxist Approach to Slogans,", undated (Box-folder 6: 8)
  - "Material Base of Thought,", undated (Box-folder 6: 9)
  - "On the USSR Theses,", undated (Box-folder 6: 10)
  - "The Proletarian Viewpoint,", undated (Box-folder 6: 11)
  - Untitled writing re American history, undated (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - Untitled writing re antisemitism, undated (Box-folder 7: 2)
  - Untitled writing re atomic energy, undated (Box-folder 7: 3)
  - Untitled writing re Nikolai Bukharin, undated (Box-folder 7: 4)
  - Untitled writing re China, undated (Box-folder 7: 5)
  - Untitled writing re Communist International 1st Congress, undated (Box-folder 7: 6)
  - Untitled writing re Darwinism, undated (Box-folder 7: 7)
  - Untitled writing re fascism, undated (Box-folder 7: 8)
  - Untitled writing re Ludwig Feuerbach, undated (Box-folder 7: 9)
  - Untitled writing re Karl Kautsky, undated (Box-folder 7: 10)
  - Untitled writing re John Maynard Keynes, undated (Box-folder 7: 11)
  - Untitled writing re V. I. Lenin, undated (Box-folder 7: 12)
  - Untitled writing re Lovestoneites, undated (Box-folder 7: 13)
  - Untitled writing re Vaclav Machajski, undated (Box-folder 7: 14)
  - Untitled writing re Russian Revolution, undated (Box-folder 7: 15)
  - Untitled writing re Iakov Sverdlov, undated (Box-folder 7: 16)
  - Untitled writing re Leo Tolstoy, undated (Box-folder 7: 17)
  - Untitled miscellaneous writings, undated (Box-folder 7: 18)
- Writings by Others, 1933-1955
  Arranged alphabetically by author. Includes manuscripts translated and/or edited for publication by Wright.
  - Cannon, James P.,"The Struggle for a Proletarian Party." Socialist Workers Party, Internal Bulletin, 1940 April (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - Commission of Inquiry into the Charges Made Against Leon Trotsky in the Moscow Trials. The Case of Leon Trotsky, 1937 (Box-folder 8: 2)
  - Dewey, Frank. "Rudolf Hilferding,", undated (Box-folder 8: 3)
  - Dobbs, Farrell, Morris Stein, and Joseph Hansen. "Statement on the Internal Party Situation,", 1953 (Box-folder 8: 4)
  - Fischer, Oscar
    - "Die Stalinisten erinnern sich an Thälmann: Warum hat Stalin nicht geholfen?", 1939-1940 (Box-folder 8: 5)
    - "Verfall und Aufstieg: Wanderer ins Nichts,", circa 1941 (Box-folder 8: 6)
  - International Communist League. "War and the Fourth International,", 1934 (Box-folder 8: 7)
    Drafted by Leon Trotsky. Printed copy with editorial annotations and notes by Wright.
  - Johre. Untitled writing re Thomas Mann, undated (Box-folder 8: 8)
    Typescript (in English) edited and likely translated by Wright.
  - Kim, Chang Sei. Untitled memoirs of a Korean physician, undated (Box-folder 8: 9)
  - Meyer, F. "Antwort auf die Anmerkungen Gen. Yalts,", undated (Box-folder 8: 10)
    Includes a holograph.
  - Morrow, Felix. "The Myth of French Democracy,", circa 1940 (Box 8: 11)
  - Munis, Grandizo
    - "Una internacional contra el internacionalismo,", 1941 February (Box-folder 8: 12)
    - "The Stagnation of Political Centrism,", undated (Box-folder 8: 13)
  - O'Rourke, Walter. Untitled writing re Mexico, 1941 June 8 (Box-folder 8: 14)
  - Parti Communiste Internationaliste [France]. "The Conception of the Party,", circa 1945 (Box-folder 8: 15)
  - Peng, Shu-tse. "The Third Chinese Revolution and Its Perspective,", 1954 December 1 (Box-folder 8: 16)
  - Plekhanov, Georgii. "Belinsky and Rational Reality," Fourth International, 1955 Spring
    - Typescript translated by Wright (Box-folder 8: 17)
    - Notes and working materials for translation (Box-folder 8: 18)
    - Printed copy (Box-folder 8: 19)
  - R. "Theses on the Crisis of Stalinist Bonapartism,", 1941 January 31 (Box-folder 8: 20)
  - Revolutionary Communist Party [China]. "The Founding Convention of the Revolutionary Communist Party of China,", 1948 September 10 (Box-folder 8: 21)
  - Rizzi, Bruno. "La bureaucratisation du monde,", 1939 (Box-folder 8: 22)
  - Sternberg, Fritz. "Draft of the Economic Part of the Program of the Fourth International,", undated (Box-folder 8: 23)
  - Trotsky, Leon
    - "Will Japan Commit Suicide?" Liberty, 1933 November 18 (Box-folder 9: 1)
    - "Politics in the Reichstag Trial," New Republic, 1934 January 3 (Box-folder 9: 2)
    - "If America Should Go Communist," Liberty, 1935 March 23 (Box-folder 9: 3)
    - "How Should the Bolshevik-Leninists Act in Spain? Letter to a Spanish Comrade,", 1936 April 12 (Box-folder 9: 4)
    - "Revolutionary Interlude in France," Nation, 1936 August 8 (Box-folder 9: 5)
    - Transcript of answers to American comrades, 1937 (Box-folder 9: 6)
    - "Did Stalin Poison Lenin?" Liberty, 1940 August 10 (Box-folder 9: 7)
    - Stalin, 1941
      - Working materials provided by Wright (Box-folder 9: 8)
      - Memoranda by Wright, Charles Malamuth and Jean van Heijenoort re editorial changes to text made by Malamuth (Box-folder 9: 9)
    - Miscellaneous writings. (Box-folder 9: 10)
  - Wollenberg, Erich. "The Red Army,", 1938 (Box-folder 9: 11)
  - Unidentified writers
    - "La montée revolutionnaire atteint l'URSS,", 1953 (Box-folder 9: 12)
    - "Report on Yugoslavia,", 1950 May (Box-folder 9: 13)
    - "Zwei Kamenews, zwei Lebenswege,", undated (Box-folder 9: 14)
    - Untitled writing re Palestine, undated (Box-folder 9: 15)
      Includes a holograph (in German).
    - Untitled series of writings on women and socialism, undated (Box-folder 9: 16)
- Miscellany, 1941-1953
  Printed matter and artwork.
  - Leaflets, cards, and style sheet, undated (Box-folder 9: 17)
  - Printed matter. Issues of Les cahiers de l'économie soviétique and clippings, 1941-1953 (Box-folder 9: 18)
  - Artwork for press, undated (Box-folder 9: 19)